Register to the Paul Hollander papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul Hollander papers
1961-2006
2007C23
Hollander, Paul, 1932-
13 manuscript boxes (5.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, curricular materials, and questionnaires, relating mainly to attitudes of American intellectuals toward communist countries and of American visitors to communist countries.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1932 Born, Budapest, Hungary
1956 Left Hungary, taking up residence in Great Britain and then the United States
1959 B.A., London School of Economics
1960 M.A., University of Illinois, Champaign-Urbana
1963 Ph.D., Princeton University
1963-1968 Assistant professor, Department of Social Relations, Harvard University
1968-2000 Associate professor and professor, Department of Sociology, University of Massachusetts at Amherst
1973 Author, Soviet and American Society: A Comparison
1981 Author, Political Pilgrims: Travels of Western Intellectuals in the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba, 1928-1978
1983 Author, The Many Faces of Socialism: Comparative Sociology and Politics
1988 Author, The Survival of the Adversary Culture: Social Criticism and Political Escapism in American Society
1992 Author, Anti-Americanism: Critiques at Home and Abroad, 1965-1990
1992 Author, Decline and Discontent: Communism and the West Today
1999 Author, Political Will and Personal Belief: The Decline and Fall of Soviet Communism
2002 Author, Discontents: Postmodern and Postcommunist
2006 Author, The End of Commitment: Intellectuals, Revolutionaries and Political Morality
2009 Author, The Only Superpower: Reflections on Strength, Weakness, and Anti-Americanism
2011 Author, Extravagant Expectations: New Ways to Find Romantic Love in America
Scope and Content of Collection
The Paul Hollander Papers in the Hoover Institution Archives consist of materials donated by Hollander in 2007, with subsequent increments. They document only a portion of Hollander's work as a sociologist and author. This work concentrated on the study of the political commitment of intellectuals, Western fellow travelers of the Soviet Union and other Communist bloc countries, sources of anti-Americanism within the United States and abroad, and leftist disillusionment in the wake of the collapse of Communist regimes in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe.
The largest volume of material in the collection is in the Research Projects and Proposals series. This series is especially notable because of its inclusion of much sociological raw data, accumulated and used by Hollander in some of his books, but susceptible to further analysis and use. Substantial data from five projects are included in the collection. The most voluminous data are in the form of questionnaire responses by American visitors to the Soviet Union in 1966. Hollander made use of this data in his book Anti-Americanism: Critiques at Home and Abroad, 1965-1990 (1992) and in a journal article in Society (2007). A second bloc of questionnaire responses on attitudes toward the United States was submitted by Canadian academics in 1989. A third bloc of questionnaire responses on political attitudes was made by members of the conservative National Association of Scholars in 1995.
In 1994 Hollander elicited free-form written replies from readers of an ad he placed in The Nation. American supporters of the Soviet Union or other Communist bloc countries were invited to describe the sources of their political commitment and how they had modified or reassessed it in the light of world events. Hollander drew upon these replies, present in the collection, in his book The End of Commitment: Intellectuals, Revolutionaries and Political Morality (2006). Another group of transcripts and summaries of interviews of intellectuals from the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe was made about the same time, dealt with the same questions, and is also present in the collection.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Americans--Communist countries.; Communism and intellectuals.; Intellectuals--United States.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1967-2007. (Box 1)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by correspondent
  - General, 1967-2007 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Ethics and Public Policy Center (Ernest W. Lefever), 1985-1989. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes proposal for publication on the Institute for Policy Studies and related correspondence
  - Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, 1984-1986 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Horowitz, Irving Louis (Transaction Books), 1987-2003 (Folder 1: 4)
  - John M. Olin Foundation, 1982-1989 (Folder 1: 5)
- Events File, 1985-1998.
  Conference papers, programs, correspondence and press coverage, arranged chronologically by event
  - Moral Equivalence: False Images of Soviet and U.S. Values: Seminar, Washington, D.C., 1985 May 1-2. (Folder 1: 6)
    Conference papers and abstract
  - Interdisciplinary Social Science Conference of Hungarian and Hungarian-Born Political Scientists and Sociologists, Hungarian Academy of Sciences, Budapest, 1988 May 15-20. (Folder 1: 7)
    Program and correspondence
  - Marxismen, Historien og de Intellektuelle: Conference, Roskilde Universitetscenter, Denmark, 1997 November 24-26. (Folder 1: 8)
    Program, correspondence and press coverage
  - Late Cold-War Perception Roundtable (Rand Corporation), Washington, D.C., 1998 July 9-10. (Folder 1: 9)
    Letter and list of participants
- Speeches and Writings, 1973-2008. (Box 2)
  Typescripts, with associated correspondence and reviews, arranged chronologically
  - Soviet and American Society: A Comparison, Publisher correspondence, 1973 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Political Pilgrims: Travels of Western Intellectuals to the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba, 1928-1978, 1981
    - Correspondence. Includes publisher correspondence, reactions of readers, and reactions to reviews (Folder 2: 2)
    - Italian edition, 1988 (Folder 2:)
    - Preface. Typescript (in English) and correspondence (Folder 2: 3)
    - Reviews (in Italian, with some English translations). Includes some correspondence (Folder 2: 4)
  - The End of Commitment: Intellectuals, Revolutionaries and Political Morality, Typescript, 2006 (Folder 2: 5-7)
  - Hungary under Communism, 2008 (Folder 2: 8)
    (Internet Global Museum on Communism contribution). Typescript and correspondence
- Academic Course Materials, 1961-1999. (Box 3-4)
  Course outlines, reading lists, examination questions, lecture notes and student papers, arranged alphabetically by course
  - Political Sociology courses
    - Course outlines and reading lists (Folder 3: 1)
    - Examination questions (Folder 3: 2)
    - Lecture notes (Folder 3: 3)
  - Social Problems courses. Course outlines, examination questions and lecture notes (Folder 3: 4)
  - Sociology of Crime and Deviance courses. Course outlines and examination questions (Folder 3: 5)
  - Sociology of Literature and Mass Culture courses
    - Course outlines and reading lists (Folder 3: 6)
    - Examination questions (Folder 3: 7)
    - Student papers (Folder 4: 1)
  - Soviet Society courses
    - Course outlines and reading lists (Folder 4: 2-3)
    - Examination questions (Folder 4: 4)
    - Lecture notes (Folder 4: 5-6)
- Research Projects and Proposals, 1966-2001. (Box 5-16.)
  Proposals, correspondence, questionnaire responses, interview transcripts and summaries, and other written responses, regarding social science research projects, arranged chronologically
  - Soviet Travel Project, 1966
    In this project Hollander asked American travelers to the Soviet Union to fill out questionnaires assessing their knowledge of and attitude toward the Soviet Union and their attitude toward the United States before and after their trips. The questionnaires were distributed to two groups of travelers, one to participants in a person-to-person exchange program sponsored by the Citizen Exchange Corps, and the other to members of the American Mathematical Society attending an international conference in Moscow. Hollander made use of the responses in his book Anti-Americanism: Critiques at Home and Abroad, 1965-1990 (1992) and in a Society journal article (2007)
    - Correspondence
      - General (Folder 5: 1)
      - American Mathematical Society (Folder 5: 2)
      - Citizen Exchange Corps (Folder 5: 3)
    - Background material regarding social science surveys in general and regarding travelers to the Soviet Union in general (Folder 5: 4)
    - Preparatory material. Notes, questionnaire drafts and coding materials, and lists of survey participants (Folder 5: 5)
    - Pilot questionnaires (Folder 5: 6)
    - Questionnaire responses by Citizen Exchange Corps group participants before trip (Folder 5: 7)
    - Questionnaire responses by Citizen Exchange Corps group participants before trip (contd.) (Folder 6: 1-4)
    - Questionnaire responses by Citizen Exchange Corps group participants before trip (contd.) (Folder 7: 1-4)
    - Questionnaire responses by Citizen Exchange Corps group participants before trip (contd.) (Folder 8: 1-2)
    - Questionnaire responses by Citizen Exchange Corps group participants after trip (Folder 8: 3-4)
    - Questionnaire responses by Citizen Exchange Corps group participants after trip (contd.) (Folder 9: 1-4)
    - Questionnaire responses by Citizen Exchange Corps group participants after trip (contd.) (Folder 10: 1-2)
    - Questionnaire responses by American Mathematical Society group participants before trip (Folder 10: 3-4)
    - Questionnaire responses by American Mathematical Society group participants before trip (contd.) (Folder 11: 1-3)
    - Questionnaire responses by American Mathematical Society group participants after trip (Folder 11: 4)
    - Questionnaire responses by American Mathematical Society group partipants after trip (contd.) (Folder 12: 1-2)
    - Questionnaire responses flagged by Hollander as exemplifying positive assessments of the United States (Folder 12: 3)
    - Questionnaire responses flagged by Hollander as exemplifying moderately negative assessments of the United States (Folder 12: 4)
    - Questionnaire responses flagged by Hollander as exemplifying strongly negative assessments of the United States (Folder 12: 5)
    - Blank questionnaires (Folder 12: 6)
    - Blank questionnaires (contd.) (Folder 13: 1)
    - Tabulations of responses (Folder 13: 2)
  - Cult of Personality in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe Project Proposal, 1975 (Folder 13: 3)
    Proposals and correspondence
  - Anti-Americanism Study Project Proposal, 1979-1984. (Folder 13: 4)
  - Canadian Academic Survey Project, 1989
    In this project Hollander asked faculty members of Canadian universities to fill out questionnaires assessing their attitudes toward the United States
    - General. Correspondence and coding data (Folder 13: 5)
    - Questionnaire responses (Folder 13: 6)
    - Questionnaire responses (contd.) (Folder 14: 1-2)
  - Disillusionment with Communist Systems Project, 1991-1995.
    Project to interview intellectuals and former party or government officials in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe regarding disillusionment with communism
    - General. Proposals and correspondence (Folder 14: 5)
    - Interview transcripts and summaries (Folder 14: 6)
  - Political Commitment Project, 1994-1995.
    Project to solicit free-form written responses (letters or essays) from American leftists regarding their political commitments and reassessments of commitments. Hollander made use of the responses in his book The End of Commitment: Intellectuals, Revolutionaries and Political Morality (2006)
    - General. Notes, proposals and correspondence (Folder 15: 1)
    - Responses flagged by Hollander as indicating change of attitude (Folder 15: 2)
    - Responses flagged by Hollander as indicating modified commitment
      - General (Folder 15: 3)
      - Amery, Al. Lengthy memoir regarding experiences as a member of the Communist Party, U.S.A. and as a member of the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War (Folder 15: 4)
    - Responses flagged by Hollander as indicating no change of attitude (Folder 15: 5)
  - National Association of Scholars Project, 1995
    In this project, commissioned by the National Association of Scholars, Hollander asked members of the association to fill out questionnaires assessing their political attitudes and reasons for joining the association
    - Correspondence and background material (Folder 15: 6)
    - Questionnaire responses (Folder 15: 7)
    - Questionnaire responses (contd.) (Folder 16: 1-2)
    - Transcribed responses (Folder 16: 3)
  - The Social and the Personal: Novels and the Ends of Our Lives Project Proposal, 2001 (Folder 16: 4)
    Correspondence regarding proposed book on literature and society